Joseph Cornell
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
- Correspondence, 1909-1982, Series 2:; (boxes 1-5; 4.2 linear feet)
  - General Correspondence, 1909-1982, 2.1:
    - Le Clerq, Tanaquil, 1956-1959, 1969-1970, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Leve, Sandra and Harvey, 1967-1968, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Levy, Julien, 1953-1967, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Life Magazine (David Bourdon), 1967, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Lousada, Pat, 1963-1968, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Loy, Mina, 1942, 1950-1951, 1982, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - L, 1952-1972, undated, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 9-10)
      Includes postcard and Christmas card from Tilly Losch (See also Series 4).
    - Matta, Roberto and Malitte (See also Piero Dorazio dossier in Series 4), 1945-1966, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Merkel, Katherine, 1965, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Messer, Tom (Guggenheim Museum), 1966-1967, 1970, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Monnier, Jackie, 1967-1970, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Moore, Lillian, 1955-1962, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Moore, Marianne, 1944, 1959, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Motherwell, Robert, 1946-1972, undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
      Includes illustrated letters and photos of Motherwell and Maria Ferreira; see also 4.1.
    - Murray Avenue School, 4th Grade Class, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - M, 1951-1972, undated, (3 folders) (Box 3, Folder 19-21)
      Includes letters from: Metropolitan Museum of Art and Museum of Modern Art.
    - N.W. Ayer and Son, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Namuth, Hans, 1968-1972, undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Neumann, J.B., 1946-1947 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - New York Institute for the Education of the Blind, 1962, 1970-1971, undated (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Nodturft, Pauline, 1964, undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - N, 1961-1972, undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - O'Doherty, Brian, 1967-1969, undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - O, 1909, circa 1938, 1965-1972, undated (Box 3, Folder 29)
      Includes letters from Oberlin College and actress Merle Oberon.
    - Page, Geraldine, 1959-1961, undated (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - P, 1927, 1947-1971, undated (Box 3, Folder 31)
      Includes letters from Pasadena Art Museum.
    - Reigel, Anne, 1968-1969, undated (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Richter, Hans, 1960-1961 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Rose, Isadora, 1962-1963, undated (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Rothko, Mark and family, 1957-1959, undated (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - R, 1948-1972, undated, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 36-37)
    - Saint, Eva Marie, 1964-1972, undated (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Schneeman, Carolee, 1964-1965 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Schoelkopf, Robert, 1960-1968, undated (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Schutte, Terry, 1965-1969, undated (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Sekula, Sonia, 1944-1951, undated (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Serbanne, Claude, 1945-1946, undated (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Shainberg, Lawrence, 1970, undated (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Siskind, Aaron, 1951, 1972, undated (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Sitney, P. Adams, 1963, undated (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Smillie, Gwen Van Dam, 1955-1972, undated (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Smith, Lois and Moon, 1957-1971, undated (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Somers, Barbara, 1965-1970, undated (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - S, 1945-1973, undated, (3 folders) (Box 3, Folder 50-52)
      Includes letters from: Peter Schjeldahl, Harold Schonberg (The New York Times), Ladislas Segy (Segy Gallery), Susan Sontag, Stable Gallery (Eleanor Ward), Allan Stone, the secretary of actress Gloria Swanson, and Katherine Sergava Szyncer.
    - Tandy, Jessica, 1947-1949, undated (Box 3, Folder 53)
      Includes a piece from the dress Tandy wore onstage in A Streetcar Named Desire.
    - Tanning, Dorothea, 1945-1965, undated (Box 3, Folder 54)
      Includes illustrated letters, pencil drawing, and a handmade book by Tanning.
    - Tchelitchew, Pavel, 1940-1943, 1955, 1964, undated (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - Thode, Elizabeth (New York Institute for the Education of the Blind), 1960-1972 (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - Thoeren, Manina, 1951, undated (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - Toumanova, Tamara, 1941-1945, 1967, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
      Includes pieces of material from Toumanova's Firebird, Giselle, and Capricio costumes, as well as a dried flower from her garden and a St. Christopher pin.
    - Tyler, Parker, 1939-1955, 1967, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - T,1933-1960, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - U, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Victor, Joan Berg and Daniel, 1964-1972, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - V, 1934-1971, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Wade, Jane, 1959-1972, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Waldman, Diane (Guggenheim Museum) and Paul, 1967, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Whitney Museum of American Art, 1962-1963, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Windham, Donald, 1946-1970, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Winter, Marian Hannah, 1948-1952 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - W, 1934, 1951-1972, undated, (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 12-13)
      Includes letters from: Glenway Wescott, Monroe Wheeler (Museum of Modern Art), Trevor Winkfield, Jerome Paul Witkin, Worcester Art Museum, and actress Fay Wray.
    - Young, Vivienne, 1966-1970 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Z, 1963, undated (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Unidentified Collage Letters, undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Unidentified and Miscellaneous Letters, 1944-1971, undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Family Correspondence, 1909-1977, 2.2:
    Subseries consists of correspondence between Cornell and various members of his immediate family, including his mother, Helen S. Cornell, his sisters, Betty Cornell Benton (often addressed as Nell) and Helen Jagger, his nieces, Sissy (Jagger) Batcheller and Jean (Jagger) Plitt, and various cousins. Some printed material, primarily clippings sent to Cornell by his mother while she was living in Westhampton during her last years, can also be found. Subseries also consists of correspondence between and amongst other members of the family, including many of those listed above, as well as Cornell's brother, Robert (subseries includes only correspondence from him), his father, Joseph I. Cornell, and his cousins, Grace Sayres and Janet (Voorhis) Traphagen. Correspondence received by Robert Cornell can be found amongst his papers in Series 11.
    Cornell's family correspondence documents his close and on-going relationships with his mother, sisters, and nieces; the large role that his family played in both his personal and creative life; the many interests he shared with his siblings, including art, literature, music, and Christian Science; and his collaborative work on collages with his sister, Betty. The one important family relationship not explicitly documented in the correspondence is Cornell's relationship with his brother, Robert. Since they lived together up until the month before Robert died, they did not exchange letters in a regular fashion. Some cards and notes between the two are scattered amongst Cornell's personal papers and diaries, as well as amongst Robert's papers. To a certain extent, Cornell's diary entries also document his relationship with his brother.
    Family correspondence files are arranged alphabetically according to the surname of the correspondent. Items within the files are arranged in rough chronological order.
    - Batcheller, Sissy (to and from Cornell), 1963-1970, undated (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Benton, Betty Cornell (to and from Cornell), 1948-1972, undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Benton, Betty Cornell (to and from other family members), 1919-1925, undated (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Cornell, Helen S. (to and from Cornell), circa 1920, 1953, 1963-1967, undated (Box 4, Folder 21)
      Includes letters from Cornell while he was a student at Andover.
    - Cornell, Joseph I. (to and from other family members), 1909, 1916 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Cornell, Robert (to Nell and Jack Benton), 1921-1965, undated, (16 folders) (Box 4, Folder 23-38)
    - Cornell, Robert (to Nell and Jack Benton), Postcards, 1934-1958, (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 39-40)
    - Cornell, Robert (to Nell and Jack Benton), Greeting Cards, 1942-1965, undated, (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 41-42)
    - Cornell, Robert (to Nell and Jack Benton), Greeting Cards, 1942-1965, undated, (4 folders) (Box 5, Folder 1-4)
    - Cornell, Robert (to Helen S. Cornell), Greeting Cards, 1961, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Cornell, Robert (to Helen, Archie, and Sissy Jagger), 1935-1941, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Cornell, Robert (to Emma Storms), 1920-1925, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Hand, Ray (to Cornell), 1966, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Jagger, Helen (to and from Cornell), 1960-1971, undated, (3 folders) (Box 5, Folder 9-11)
    - McMonegal family (to Cornell), 1945-1971, 1977, undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Plitt, Jean (to and from Cornell), 1946-1971, undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Sayres, Grace (to other family members), 1950-1971, undated, (4 folders) (Box 5, Folder 14-17)
      Includes letters to Helen S. Cornell (dating from 1950 to 1964) and to Betty Cornell Benton and siblings (dating from 1966 to 1971).
    - Storms, Ethel (to Cornell), undated (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Traphagen, Janet (to Cornell and his mother), 1965-1966, undated (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Greeting Cards, 1956-1972, 2.3:
    Subseries consists of holiday and birthday greeting cards to Cornell from family, friends, colleagues, and acquaintances, as well as some greeting cards that were signed by Cornell but never sent.
    Greeting cards are arranged in general alphabetical files according to correspondent. Unidentified, miscellaneous, and unsent cards are arranged in files at the end of the subseries.
    - A, 1968-1971, undated (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - B, 1962-1972, undated, (4 folders) (Box 5, Folder 21-24)
    - C, 1960-1972, undated (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - D, 1957-1970, undated (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - E, 1956-1971, undated (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - F, 1968-1969, undated (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - G, 1968-1970, undated (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - H, 1966-1970, undated (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - I-J, 1965-1969, undated (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - K-L, 1960-1970, undated (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - M, 1957-1971, undated (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - N-O, 1969-1970 (Box 5, Folder 34)
    - P, 1960-1972, undated (Box 5, Folder 35)
    - R, 1962, undated (Box 5, Folder 36)
    - S, 1956-1971, undated (Box 5, Folder 37)
    - T, 1966-1972, undated (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - U, 1957-1972, undated (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - W, 1962-1972, undated (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - Unidentified and Miscellaneous, 1966-1969, undated (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - Unsent Cards, 1968-1970, undated (Box 5, Folder 42)
- Diaries, 1941-1973, Series 3:; (boxes 6-10; 5 linear feet)
  Series is comprised of Cornell's diaries, which are unconventional in form, consisting of entries, notes, and writings recorded on loose sheets and scraps of paper, as well as in the margins of newspapers, on the backs of used envelopes, on creased paper bags, napkins, labels, train tickets, library slips, blank telegram forms, calling cards, and parts of bakery boxes. Included are other items, such as TV Guide pages, dried leaves and flowers, cutouts, plastic and metal objects, and a part of a whisk broom, collected by Cornell presumably because they related, in one way or another, to what he was recording.
  Diaries record Cornell's day-to-day experiences (sometimes in very minute detail), with allusions to: the books he read, the music he listened to, the films he watched, and the many "sparkings" he received from them; his various finds ("trouvailles") while hunting for material; his thoughts and practices relating to Christian Science; the meals and snacks he ate; the places he went and the sights he saw during his city wanderings; the evocations brought on by ordinary, everyday things; the tensions at home; the people who visited him; the "teeners," "fees," and other women who captured his imagination; his dreamings and awakenings; and his thoughts, feelings, impressions, and ideas during the course of a day.
  Diaries also record and reflect on Cornell's various art projects, with references to particular box constructions, box series, collages, and films on which he is working, and to ideas and inspirations for new projects, as well as some commentary on his chosen mediums, the creative process, and the final products. They explore many of the themes that recur in Cornell's art work, including, among others, his fascination with actresses and ballerinas of the past and present, and his abiding appreciation of birds, the night sky, and nature. They also reflect on many of the ideas and concerns underlying his art work and other creative activities, such as his preoccupation with the past, his notions of "metaphysique d'ephemera" (the metaphysical aspects of ephemera) and "the beauty of the commonplace," and his concern to recapture past experiences in his art works and other projects.
  Diaries record and reflect on Cornell's wide-ranging "explorations," ranging from GC 44 (with references to his initial experiences during the time he was working at the Garden Centre nursery, and to his subsequent and on-going attempts to recreate the flavor and atmosphere of those days) to Portrait of Ondine (with references to the early inspirations of discovering a portrait of Fanny Cerrito and of seeing a vision of her in a warehouse window, and to his later efforts to compile and create an "unauthorized biography" of the ballerina). They also refer to his many other creative activities, including various research and collecting ventures, such as regular browsing in secondhand book stalls and stores, visits to the library, accumulating material and compiling files on people and topics; and various publishing ventures, such as his contributions to Dance Index and View, and his self-publications, Maria and Bel Canto Pet. They comment on the act of keeping a diary, expressing many times over some of Cornell's deepest concerns about the necessity and difficulty of trying to capture experience "before it fades" and the discrepancy between the original experience and the "cataloguing" of it in writing.
  Diaries document Cornell's on-going preoccupations with certain historical and cultural figures, such as the ballerinas, Marie Taglioni and Fanny Cerrito, the singers, Maria Malibran and Raquel Meller, various composers (from Mozart to Satie), the author, Gerard de Nerval, the artists, Delacroix and Vermeer, and various actresses of stage and screen (from Jeanne Eagels to Claire Bloom). Later diaries are taken up with Cornell's episodic preoccupations with various young women he encountered along Main Street (waitresses and shopgirls) or at home ("helpers," young artists, and friends).
  Distinguishing between consistently dated material that was organized into chronological files and mostly undated material that was organized into bulk files, the Diaries series is arranged into two subseries:
  3.1: Diary Entries, 1941-1972
  3.2: Diary Notations, 1941-1973
  - Diary Entries, 1941-1972, 3.1:
    Subseries consists of files of consistently dated entries, notes, writings, and other material. The files, which comprise the vast majority of the series, are arranged chronologically according to how Cornell likely accumulated, maintained, and used them. The bulk of the entries are hand-written, though typed entries are common during the period from the mid-1940s to the mid-1950s. The extent of the diaries, both in number and length of entries, increases with each year Cornell kept them. In the later diaries, it is not uncommon to find several entries for a given day.
    The file descriptions below are meant to provide researchers with some sense of the contents of Cornell's diary entries, but are by no means exhaustive.
    - 1941-1944 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      Includes references to: Ondine box, Fanny Cerrito, and article on Hedy Lamarr for View magazine; various entries for 1944 written in 1947; as well as writings, "Windows and Fanny Cerrito, Discovery - 1940" and "Fanny Cerrito Album" (with some comments by Marianne Moore).
    - 1945 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      Includes references to: a phone conversation with Mina Loy, Bacall box, "Clowns, Elephants and Ballerinas" project for Dance Index, 3rd swan box, principle of "metaphysique d'ephemera," Christian Science (abbreviated as C.S.), and meeting with Salvador Dali.
    - 1946 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      Includes references to: owl box, natural history boxes, Lauren Bacall box, Jennifer Jones Clown Box, reminiscences and evocations (instances when one thing reminds him of another thing), and "the beauty of the commonplace."
    - 1947 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      Includes references to: Soap Bubble Set series, Homage to Romantic Ballet, C.S. treatment, Gerard de Nerval, GC 44, meeting with Louise Bourgeois in the library, "Aeolus" perfume spread for Vogue, and parrot box; as well as entries for 1944.
    - 1948 (Box 6, Folder 5)
      Includes references to: "lattice" bird box, Bacall box, fixing up cellar for a workshop, Jean Cocteau's film La Belle et la Bete, C.S., and GC 44; as well as writings, "A White Crested Cockatoo (for Blanche DuBois)," dedicated to Tennessee Williams, and "The Sign of the Sparrow," reminiscencing about Mr. Goldsmith's bookshop.
    - 1949 (Box 6, Folder 6)
      Includes references to: Raquel Meller (Spanish singer of Gypsy love songs), Rose Hobart film, GC 44, and Hans Christian Andersen.
    - 1950 (Box 6, Folder 7)
      Includes references to: Vermeer, a "mechanism" for the new "hotel" windows, Dove Cote #2, de Kooning's statement about the "architecture" of the bird boxes, work space, parakeet box, Aviary series, Raquel Meller, new Soap Bubble Sets, Parmigianino box, work for Vogue, "Moutarde Dijon" box, Night Songs exhibition, and windowed constellation boxes.
    - January-May1951 (Box 6, Folder 8)
      Includes references to: Night Songs exhibition, bird boxes, the Ondine experience of years ago, Sand Fountains, Figaro cover for Vogue, Garden Center, dream (night of April 16th), GC 44, "Windows and Fanny Cerrito," and the habit of accumulating.
    - June-September1951 (Box 6, Folder 9)
      Includes references to: new Hotel box, bird box, Ondine, "Hotel Pelican," Vermeer box, Chocolate Menier, Gozzoli box, trip to Westhampton (September), "Hotel de l'Univers," "Hotel Observatoire," GC 44, observations of the night sky, Matta letter, and Lesson Sermons.
    - October-December1951 (Box 6, Folder 10)
      Includes references to: "compartment" letter to Matta, Adirondack vacation of 1921 or 1922, "Sonia Sekula box," Colombier box, Sailor's star box, "Hotel Savoi" cockatoo, "Hotel de l'Univers #2," "Hotel s. Lumiere (Gozzoli de Medici)," "Hotel Observatoire," and variant of Medici Slot Machine; as well as a version of letter to de Kooning and an article excerpt, "No Artist Can Be His Own Universe" by Sidney J. Harris (copied by Cornell).
    - January-February1952 (Box 6, Folder 11)
      Includes references to: Giuditta Pasta (19th-century Italian opera singer), feelings about romantic ladies of the past, show at the Egan Gallery, Mozart, Schumann, and Beethoven.
    - March-April1952 (Box 6, Folder 12)
      Includes references to: Westhampton Fall '51 entries, works in progress like Portrait of Ondine, Crystal Cage, and The Floral Still Life, GC 44 experiences, and the "ephemera of faces seen but once."
    - May-June1952 (Box 6, Folder 13)
      Includes references to: making cellar into a more dignified workroom, a discovery in the bookshop, Colombier wooden balls, sand fountains, and The Celestial Aviary; as well as writing, "Dog-Day Jottings."
    - July-August1952 (Box 6, Folder 14)
      Includes references to: the Cerrito album, "wandering," and the living present as an antidote to too much speculation about the past.
    - September-October1952 (Box 6, Folder 15)
      Includes references to: new versions of Rose Hobart film, trip to Westhampton; as well as a version of letter to Elizabeth Pollett.
    - November-December1952 (Box 6, Folder 16)
      Includes references to: Night Sky box, evocations of former train trips to the city, Nostalgia of Sea collage, Bird with Shoe-Button Eyes, Little Dancer, reading Emily Dickinson (abbreviated as E.D.), and time of "Climate of Eden" activity; as well as an entry labeled "non-diary."
    - January-February1953 (Box 6, Folder 17)
      Includes references to: rediscovery of E.D., GC 44, Nedick's store windows, the "Aviary" experiences, Night Voyage exhibit, "Figurehead Soap Bubble Set," Claire Bloom box, and new Medici box; as well as a version of letter to Geraldine Page.
    - March-April1953 (Box 6, Folder 18)
      Includes references to: diary keeping, "delight in the commonplace," working on Pinturicchio Boy, dream of Zizi Jeanmarie, the New York Public Library, Antiques Fair, Delacroix, and Rothko.
    - May-June1953 (Box 6, Folder 19)
      Includes references to: Pasta, the opera "Cenerentola" (Cinderella), the Raquel Meller period, the Somnambula LP, Magritte's "Empire of Lights," inspiration for developing boxes of the architectural type with poster walls and heads of youth, preoccupation with working in another medium or format, work on Medici prince, "find" of Racine (1808), Bibliomania project, and diary keeping.
    - July1953 (Box 6, Folder 20)
      Includes references to: wanderlust, "pull" between working on boxes and "explorations," "Sylphide-Apotheose (for Giuditta Pasta)," "Colombier Dove-cotes," and Elizabeth Bowen; version of letter to Mr. Huth regarding his (Cornell's) influences; version of thank-you letter to record company for Somnambula recording.
    - August1953 (Box 6, Folder 21)
      Includes references to: windows (boxes, the outlook from the Westhampton cabin, and views from subway door-opening), need for recording the present mood and impossibility of capturing the "exact flavor of days," Celestial Theater, Adelaide Crapsey, De Severac-Chabrier preoccupations, and 2nd trip to Westhampton.
    - September-October1953 (Box 6, Folder 22)
      Includes references to: going over Rilke's letters, GC 44 and Cerrito 1940 experiences, new Parmigianino box, Valerie dossier, Auriga box, a visit to the Morgan Library, and "a Parrot for Juan Gris."
    - November-December1953 (Box 6, Folder 23)
      Includes references to: GC 44, Little Dancer, Berenice experiences, Dickinson poem, Adolphe Adams (composer), "Gris" cockatoo, and Tchaikovsky's Nutcracker Suite.
    - January1954 (Box 6, Folder 24)
      Includes references to: Julie Harris in Mademoiselle Colombe, GC 44 experience, work in cellar on Medici Princess, "cellar mood," and backyard scene of birds in the quince tree.
    - February1954 (Box 6, Folder 25)
      Includes references to: Maria Malibran, Pauline Viardot-Garcia, the Cerrito experiences, sense of the past coming to life via books and experiences with browsing, deep desire to reach young people through art work, Dessert du Roi box, and the film, Children of Paradise.
    - March1954 (Box 6, Folder 26)
      Includes references to: Audrey Hepburn preoccupation and the effect of extreme temperatures.
    - April1954 (Box 6, Folder 27)
      Includes references to: sorting newspaper clippings, "The Caliph of Bagdad" heard over the radio, the "dragging McCarthy hearings," Auriga, Andromeda, GC 44, and Vermeer box.
    - May1954 (Box 6, Folder 28)
      Includes references to: 2 Juan Gris cockatoos, music (including "Caliph of Bagdad," Fourth Symphony of Mahler, Schubert octet, Haydn "Bird" quartet, and Beethoven #1 Quartet), GC 44 and Lawrence homestead "pilgrimmages," Ludwig suitcase material, Soap Bubble sets, and Raquel Meller.
    - June1954 (Box 6, Folder 29)